by Olympic silver medalist from 2004 in
the 10 metre synchro diving Leon Taylor
Leon a few things to say who are the
favorites and who's likely to be a
middle contention for this yeah good
question to start with Bob welcome to
the Aquatic Centre this place is
electric with excitement the seats are
filling up and well it'd be safe to say
that the gold medal favorites buy quite
away are the Chinese women Shah and her
Zi about to wave to declare their the
Australians could feature and I think
the Canadians as well so I would say
China Canada Australia would be the
three frontrunners but anything can
happen it's a straight final every
single one of those five dives counts
and anything can happen and driving is
an evolving sport things change every
time we bring it to you whether at home
or around the world a new scoring system
of sorts anyway this time there are
twice the amount of execution judges how
will that work and why has it been
brought in yeah thanks for the question
on the judge in there for diving trying
to improve the scoring system to make it
even fairer you're going to see plenty
of scores coming up on the screen
execution judges and synchronized judges
so the execution judges are only looking
at the diver closest to them in the
execution they obviously split on both
sides of the pool and the synchro judges
are marking solely the synchronization
of the divers it goes through a little
bit of a complicated you know patterning
sequence you basically take the highest
and lowest off each of the execution
judges so two scores carry from
execution the five synchronized judges
the highest and lowest are taken off and
then the three synchronized scores are
then added to the to execution scores
multiplied by the degree of difficulty
you with me so far and then x naught
point six to give the total we can
explain again later but what you need to
know is it's weighted towards the
synchronization so the better the
synchronization you know the better it
is for the total score for that
particular dive of course every single
dive counts let's talk about the
selection of the divers as well so the
initial two rounds we'll see everybody
do the same ones maybe not in the same
order but it's the 2.0 so yeah that's
like the limited degree of difficulty so
the first two rounds as Bob said is a
fixed degree of difficulty of two
it doesn't matter what dive you do you
get a degree of difficulty of 2.0 so
you're gonna see forward dives reverse
dives inward dives very very simple
basic beautiful dives and they're all
important execution and synchronization
you will really see you know who's
touching their toes at the same time and
on the replays you'll really get to pull
it apart
of course the judges here do not see the
replay that is just for you at home to
enjoy also only one set of divers the
Australians are doing a three point one
the highest tariffs available to the
missing cut in this competition why
they're doing that and one of the
Chinese not doing that yeah women's
springboard diving it isn't like the
men's where the men's are really pushing
the boundaries three point six is three
point eight three point nine s the women
aren't quite strong enough to perform
those incredibly difficult dives but
what they are performing is Full Tilt
for the for the female diving population
and it's interesting to see the dive
that you're talking about that three
point one is the forward
three-and-a-half somersaults in the pike
position it's a it's a busy dive things
can go wrong and the Australians
obviously coming out all guns blazing
using that one as their second of their
three optional dives and Australians of
course number two in the start list but
the Chinese pair of women Sharon Percy
are super consistent super classy and
certainly they're going to be the the
frontrunners from the start I would
predict but then again we know what can
happen sometimes in Olympic diving and
we should point out the British pair
aren't here because they have qualified
they are here because of home nation
inclusion that's correct the
qualification event Rebecca gallantry
and Alyssia blag did not earn their spot
outright they've been given a spot
because we're a host nation so
predictions today for our girls anything
above 8th will be exceptional for
performance from from their point of
view so let's wait and see so the three
meter board is about to welcome its
first visitor two of them of course it
being sync rope tannier Kenyatta and
Francesca dalip a very experienced
pairing from Italy and when competition
gets underway very shortly they'll be
going for a Ford died with pike
you'll find the majority of the dives
today will be Pike educational tuck and
the occasional free dive where they
could pretty much do whatever they want
within reason yeah almost almost it's
not holding one position for too long so
the pike position of course is folding
at the hips and keeping the knees
straight and toes pointed the judges
looking for all important entries into
the water so the relatively simple or
straightforward dives coming first tenia
can the Otto and Francesca Donna pay for
Italy it's a solid start from the
Italian pair always tricky opening up a
contest the first divers and unlike the
world championships there's no
preliminaries to get rid of the EBG bees
but the Italian girls looking pretty
steadfast there as you can see maybe
Francesca closest to us hitting the
water a fraction ahead of Tonya corny
Otto but they'll be pleased with that
dive but looking at us maybe a little
bit of difference in the distance from
the board but I think the judges yep
that's a good start that's how the
judges see it the line through a number
means it doesn't count so the 9.0 on the
right and the 8.5 in the synchro do now
to the Australian pair the Australians
are doing well in the Aquatic Centre in
the pool so far can they replicate that
on the diving Hannibal Smith and
Charlene Stratton with their opening
dive this time it's a back dive for the
Australians
it's a good start for the Australian
pair you can hear Charlene err cueing
Annabel ready go and that's the magic if
synchronized diving we're not telepathic
if we do use counting or various signals
in order to take off and as you can see
here touching the toes at the same time
I'll move back towards the water you can
see the syncro for yourself please
remember the judges do not get to see
this the marks are already into the
computer and there be appearing on your
screen shortly
the Australian coaches they like it and
I'm sure the girls will please be
pleased with that start let's see what
it brings them brings them forty nine
point two zero the eight on the left and
the eight point five Zhan the right will
count towards their total now the
red-hot favourites will mix yep and Z
and they will start with of course 2.0
as all of these will be in the opening
two rounds it's a forward dive
just beautiful as we expect laying down
their markup limited degree of
difficulty so important that you're not
trying too hard and the judges awarding
the marks for graceful aesthetically
pleasing movements and as you can see
they're women shy and he's showing their
experience beautiful synchronization
hitting the water at the same time
littered with nines I'm sure from the
judges there we go yeah you're right in
the 9.5 thrown in for good measure so
that takes their total to the biggest
total so far fifty four point zero zero
I'm proud of which there's a pretty
decent number here at the Aquatic Center
welcome the British composers Alicia
black and Rebecca gallantry they will go
with the inward dive as a starting
program or good start there from the
that's certainly the home favorites the
crowd here we're really getting into it
a siliceous mum they're sporting the
Union Jack Rebecca just getting out the
pool there let's see how the girls did
it's actually very very good synchro
holding then Rebecca closest to us
hitting the water fractionally in front
of Alicia unless you of course only 15
imagine being in front of this crowd at
only 15 years old
super slow-motion you can see there
Rebecca just hitting the water a
fraction ahead as I said so the scores
will not be as good as the Chinese but
that's a solid start for the British
pair forty-nine point eight zero is
their opening score so they're the
bottom of the pile in the early stages
Abigail Johnston and Kelsey Bryant for
the USA for dive to start their five
well that's good from the US starting
their campaign plenty of support here
for the US I know they're rocking and
rolling in Nepal and this the dive team
probably aren't as strong as it where
anywhere near as strong as a swim team
opening up their campaign here with the
forward dive pikes walking to the end of
the diving board is called the hurdle
step in diving as you can see beautiful
synchronization I think the judges or to
mate in half sand nines for the
synchronization the US judges my coaches
sports in the same haircut there and
synchronized that's a great height on
that as well wasn't it they mostly get a
lot of elevation off the board fifty two
point eight zero the Americans open up
with that
here come the Canadians to follow
definitely middle prospects for today
it's a very tried and tested pair Emily
Haman's and Jennifer Abel with their
inward dive oh wow yes I'm pretty sure
the Canadians will be looking to get in
the first diving medal very strong team
and this is a strong eventful than any
Haven obviously in a fourth Olympic
Games medals in the previous three so a
wealth of Olympic experience Jenna fable
ten years younger than Emily and there
abouts and that's a nice start for the
Canadian pair good entries into the
water fantastic synchro that's going to
put them right up there close to the
Chinese I would imagine not too far shy
of the Chinese score fifty three point
four zero compared to fifty four for the
Chinese with their opening dive for
Canada puts him in second place handle a
pang and you're not young of Malaysia
with their opening dive which is a
forward dive
well well it ended up okay but I'm sure
you'll agree with me is a little bit of
a mismatch coming into the hurdle step
there it looked like they were going to
be well out of time but ended up hitting
the water you can see here differing
times on the on the jump they somehow
managed well you could just see the
synchronization ended up okay but wow
I'm not sure what to make of that let's
see what the judges think I don't know
what you think at home either
well here's their response and it's not
terribly pleasing for Malaysian eyes I'm
afraid forty six point two zero the
takeoff all over the place they finally
got together it wasn't the end to the
ball but not a great start for Malaysia
now the Ukraine represented by Anna his
men Scott and Elena Federer over and
again you've seen a couple of times
already here comes that inward dive if
you both do but of comparing and
contrasting in the opening couple of
rounds as everybody does the same kind
of diving getting into the competition
now I would say that judges are looking
for the divers to be completely in line
and I'm sure the replay will show that
one of the divers was slightly further
away from the diving pool so they will
be penalized yeah I am correct the
churches of course don't get the benefit
of the replay but we do and you do and
so they're probably be middle of the
pack with that one maybe towards the
bottom certainly even bit better than
the Malaysians effort Hickam the scores
a point fives on the right will count in
the eight on the Left will count the
ones with the lines through do not so a
total of forty nine point two zero for
Ukraine end of the first round of the
women's synchronized 3-meter springboard
China no surprise in first place can day
USA Great Britain in fifth with forty
nine point eight zero
[Music]
[Applause]
on to round 2 of the women's
synchronized 3-meter springboard first
diving event at London 2012 and starting
the turns made a decent job of in the
first round but their forward dive here
comes the reverse dive of Tanya Kenyatta
and Francesca dalip a classy dive there
from the Italian pair and they're
certainly going to be in the hunt for a
medal here if a wealth of experience
looking to be nice to stage you see
Francesca closest to her toes hanging 10
as we call it all 10 toes over the end
of the diving board but she manages to
hold the execution who died beautifully
Connie otters father of course competed
40 years ago and won a medal in the
springboard event so certainly following
the family tradition and those are the
marks for the Italians nines and a point
fives and eight point five Zhan the left
in terms of execution we'll go through
the rigmarole of how they get to that
final score a little later on again in
case you missed the early part of it now
the Australians who have high hopes of a
medal SiC from near the bottom it comes
their reverse dive well it's a better
second round I've from a synchronization
point of view however the execution well
the all-important entry into the water
throwing up a little bit too much splash
there so the execution judges will
penalize for that but look at this
beautiful synchronization arms moving at
the same time correct distance from the
diving board all alignments in their
correct alignment there we are the super
slow-motion drop cam you can see the
divers entering the water they're trying
to spread the air that they're taking
down with them with the hands in order
to complete get the suction didn't quite
work for the Aussies oh no the execution
judges are fairly split on that score of
40 9.20 exactly the same as they scored
in the first round
Chyna leading the way this is the
reverse sorts with one
twists first we reverse one-and-a-half
somersaults half a twist of course the
limited degree of difficulty there
Chinese interesting choice of dive
actually it's a little bit more
complicated than some of the others
we've been seeing but of course the
degree of difficulty is fixed at 2.0
landing on the end of the diving board
here's the half a twist and there's the
one and a half so it's not the best
synchronization I've seen from this
Chinese pair that means it gives the
other pairs chance to stay with them of
course all changes will happen from vine
3 when their unlimited degree of
difficulty vines kick in well it's still
good marks but maybe not quite as good
as they would have hoped for fifty two
point eight zero does open the door
slightly there's ajar anyway for the
rest to follow become the home favorites
at least here black and Rebecca Gallen
treat looking for the expensive one just
say well I say straight forward forward
dive for the British pair or very good
synchronization it was good entries into
the water I think Rebecca Gallen tree
closest to us just bends at the hips as
she enters the water giving the
impression she wasn't vertical which was
a shame because actually until their
hands touched the water this had nines
written all over it I'm not sure what
the judges are going to go for
synchronization is fantastic hopefully
they're going to go certainly in my
opinion deserves some nines i loving
their costumes fantastic design all
about impressing the judges and that's a
great second round dive as it is they've
stepped it up a notch or two lines on
the right hand side total of fifty two
point two zero for the time being at
least
they're up into third place the
americans abigail johnston and you'll
see bryant and they will go for a
reverse dive again all these tariffs of
2.0
and I've been impressed we're watching
these girls in training and they're
certainly holding the kind of form that
they were showing in practice has Nick
McCrory cheering them on from the
sidelines great support for these divers
here today all about holding your nerve
this is a precision sport it's all about
consistency and the Americans certainly
coming out with a bit of consistency
some funny arm movements there but there
we go up over the top beautiful overhead
shot there I think they're going to get
some nines for that one they do they
match the British core nines in synchro
and eight point five and eight in
execution Americans go into second place
on to the Canadians following the
Americans with a forward dive second
after round one this is Emily Haman's
and Jennifer Abel
well it wasn't sure what was going on
there Bob Bob well are just looking over
to me quizzically and yes I'm not quite
sure how they were approaching the end
of the diving port there from here it's
okay so we can see on the replay arms up
into the pike shape marginally out of
time in and out of the pike shape entry
into the water is actually good
alignment just as his from the diving
board and hitting the water
jennipher they're moving very close
towards Emily trying to hold hands on
the way down oh my goodness look she was
right in the corner well done Jennifer
you did well there to hold that my
goodness that could have been much worse
than it was the Canadians still in it I
think can I call that a scruffy dive
there was nothing nice or
edifying about that die from the start
to the end was there it just didn't look
great at any stage and they were
punished for that fifty seven point four
zero the marks are down is Pam and she
on for Malaysia oh the chamois in the
water there that certainly drought dried
my attention obviously been thrown in by
one of the divers that's what the divers
used to try themselves off in between
rounds to make sure they don't slip when
they're in the shape so here we are this
is the back one-and-a-half somersaults
with the half a twist there's the half a
twist into the pike position or the free
position the Malaysians are probably a
little bit off the pace now wouldn't be
surprised if if they're towards the
bottom of the field at the end of this
contest but still a long way to go look
back at the scoreboard they'll see what
you're seeing on your screen eight the
left 8.0 s and 7.5 s will count on the
right yeah a shake of the head two going
not quite how we planned that to go and
how it went in training now these girls
need a bit of pickup as well cements get
and a fella over of Ukraine
oh it's reasonably okay you know again
the approach on the hurdle step that's
what we call the hurdle steps as they
come into the end of the diving board
seem to be a little bit ahead of time
managed to get it together in the end
the judges are inputting the scores as
we speak and let's look at the replay
yeah a little bit of overbalancing
coming into their dive you're closest to
us you can see both divers it needs to
be a mirror image so there I think only
eights for synchro maybe even a seven
and a half I'm not sure that's what you
see what the judges think
right there be
the bottom in the field I think after
the first two rounds our happy faces
they're his men Scott and feller over
eights will not cut it today they need
to be far higher up the food chain than
that China USA Italy after round two
Great Britain in fourth place just ahead
of Canada bringing up the rain on into a
hundred marks yet Australia surprisingly
a long way down at this stage where
there are three more rounds to come
Ukraine and Malaysia at the back of the
pack now the dives getting a bit more
difficult as we get to the 2.0 so up to
three point zeroes back two and a half
somersaults the third round dive of the
Italian pair of Tanya can you tow and
Francesca de la Paix it'll be performed
in the pike position
Wow this is where the competition starts
that's a fantastic opening optional dive
we've got the required out the way the
limited degree of difficulty this is
where the big guns come out and in the
female springboard event that means the
back two and a half pikes 3.0 beautiful
entry into the water finishing a little
bit low than you lower than you would
hope a little bit art-sheet both of them
doing a good impression of a banana
however the entry into the water is good
the syncro will be 8.5 s yes Wow there
you go marker down seven four point
seven zero it is for the Italian pair
that all lifts their spirits and lifts
them up the table just a little bit
after that but here come the Australians
they have their big dive to come in
round for the third round dive is an
inward two and a half somersaults
well the Aussies have got some work to
do and that probably won't help the
Inwood two and a half of course standing
backwards but having to spin forwards
towards the diving board it's dangerous
because your toes especially in the pike
position could come a little bit close
but I'm pleased to say both divers
clearing the diving board Charlene
Stratton closest to us going over a
vertical as she goes in the
synchronization is very very good I
don't think they get more than eights in
synchro and they need to do better than
that to catch the front runners yeah
eights for Cinco it is but the execution
letting them down 7.5 will count on the
left-hand side now on to the favorites
of course we have a diver in were going
for her third title in this event it is
Wu paired with her Zi this time and they
are going for inwards two-and-a-half
somersaults well there you go China just
showing their dominance
the first option all around dive and I
put a flag waving from their teammates
the replay or just show how good this
pairing is China's so strong in this
sport in which two and a half there we
go both divers finishing way above board
level plenty of time to complete the
dive almost effortlessly entries into
the water very very good good execution
nines for synchro yep there we go mystic
Leon strikes again 9.0 9.0 and 8.5 on
the execution the cheer greets the home
favorites first they're really big dive
see it for Alicia black and Rebekah
gallantry it's a reverse two and a half
somersaults was worth three point zero
in tariffs now
oh it was always the risky one if there
was a dive in their program which might
might let them down it was going to be
this one it's the reverse two and a half
which means landing on any end of the
diving board jumping up and away from
the diving board and spinning backwards
towards it the girls were in beautiful
sinker there Becky just letting go have
a shake just a little bit too early
landing shorter vertical with a bit of a
back arch it's a shame because the
synchronization is good Tom Daly they're
just showing you with his expression
what I'm telling you with my words and
the marks will indicate exactly all of
the above and all her before the
execution not great the sink are not
great ultimately it puts him down a
couple of places and actually might mean
them dropping to the bottom of the table
now on to the Americans Johnston and
Bryant going for a for two and a half
somersaults this will have one twist
involved in it as well there we go very
good from the American says certainly
going to be in the hunt if they carry on
with this consistent performance I was
watching him in training and I've been
very impressed smiles or veins here we
go forward two and a half somersaults
one twist so here's one and a half
somersaults there's one twist and
there's the completion of the two and a
half the synchronization is very good I
think they're going to get 88.5 s on the
synchro and that's going to leave them
in good stead well up there with the
frontrunners up above the Italians and
the Australians and into second place go
Abigail Johnson and Kelsey Bryant now
the Canadian Pet of Emily havens and
Jennifer Abel first of their really big
dives and is the back two and a half
somersaults fifth place after round two
but this can change very very quickly
and rapidly and we get up to the bigger
tariff and here comes the first of this
well it's good Jennifer April absolutely
nailed her back two and a half pike
Emily was good as well let's have a look
on the replay I was distracted by the
execution of Jennifer that was truly
exceptional synchronizations a little
bit off you can see there in the pike
spinning at different signs entering the
water okay so I think the judges might
go with them on that I think they might
get seven house and eights for syncro
which is a good citko score execution
might vary though let's have a look
eights on the syncro eight point five
and eight on the execution for Haman's
and abel and they're not able yet to get
into the top three on to the Malaysians
have their race run for their early
dives but there's three more to come so
perhaps they can pick things up a bit
here with their back two and a half
somersaults in the pike position relays
you at the moment
in the last place
or that isn't going to help them yeah
you can see entries into the water
they're both divers over rotating so
you'll see that is on the replay hitting
the water vertically it's obviously what
the judges are looking for and what the
divers would have been hoping for but as
you see here both over rotating so tops
of the thighs and then shins hitting the
water even a little bit of a mini tidal
wave being set off they're not quite
enough to get your surfboard tight but
there we go Malaysia quite far behind
now I would imagine when the marks come
up never really got going today have
they and those scores are for sore eyes
I'm afraid if you happen the 5.5 so
you're not really in contention and
they're not Ukraine where the Bissman
skip and the fed a robot this is their
back two and a half somersaults and
again the further back when they'd like
to be after round two they're in seventh
place oh it's pretty solid nothing
spectacular but that will certainly keep
them where they were after the first two
rounds maybe move them up a place or two
swinging the arms bending the knees
reaching up looking for enough elevation
to squeeze into this backward two and a
half obviously spinning backwards away
from the diving board a little bit of
splash being thrown up from both divers
they're probably six and a half's on the
execution 7.5 synchro let's see well I
think those marks will be generous to my
eyes for the you know 7.5 s + 6 and 6.5
doesn't really doing a great deal of
good in terms of moving up in positions
they are sick they were seventh not
really in medal contention so we are 3/5
gone China as I have done all the way
through the competition of leading
that's changing behind them USA to Italy
3 Canada 4 and Great Britain's change
might have faltered somewhat with that
round 3 dive from black and gallantry
[Music]
so on to the penultimate round of dives
in the women's synchronized 3-meter
springboard the Italians are Kenyatta
and dalla pate and with a forward two
and a half somersaults with one twist
their last but one attempt always ended
up okay in the end
they normally finish on this dive
obviously been having a little bit of
difficulty in training electing to to
put in their program a little bit
earlier let's see what happens so
landing on the end of the diving board
cono furthest away from us was a little
bit back from the end there's not very
much spring there and as you can see
she's struggling a little bit to get a
dive in in the allotted time so there's
the twist into the water it's a little
bit here and there but I still think
that will keep them in contention well
show you how the sync remarks which
you're gonna be the telling scorer here
seven point five seven and seven in
terms of a medal prospect that might be
the end of it that was not very well
executed the Australians also have a bit
of work to do Smith and Stratton they
could start by doing it with the biggest
dive of the competition there's a
forward three and a half somersaults
Pike position it is worth three point
one biggest tariff we will see in the
competition today
or high risk from the Australians the
synchronization was superb the execution
and this is why it's worth three point
one was a little bit off Charlene
closest to us they're getting out the
water actually lands short of vertical
so here we go let's count them one two
three Sharlee yes sure to vertical
they're squeezing it round I think
she'll get penalized a little bit their
synchronization was good three point one
didi look at this super slow-motion look
at the expression on the divers faces
this is a tough sport good scores though
sixty nine point seven five eight on the
right seven and six point five on the
left for the time being anyway they're
up to second be there for very long with
these two around though woo and it's yep
how's he going for their fourth dive
reverse two and a half somersaults
there you go pick the bones out of that
one my goodness me the italians opening
the door slightly for them they were the
closest ones to the Chinese and the
Chinese just showing that they are
really a cut above landing on the end of
the diving board here perfect unison
here it comes to reverse two and a half
in the pike position that's got nines
written all over it for me that could
potentially go close to 80 points let's
wait and see what the judges think but
for me that's the dive of the contest of
thus far and see too much wrong with
that could you nines on the right nine
and 8.5 on the left
execution judge is not overly enamored
with it but synchro judges loved it to
bits
that's why China have a sizable lead 23
points over the Italians at this stage
now to the Brits back in gallantry for
two and a half somersaults one twist can
they make up a position or two with this
yes I think they can is the answer to
your question Bob that's an excellent
fourth round I've obviously crossed with
themselves for the third round I've came
out kept their composure and here we are
this is a big die for them forward two
and a half somersaults one twist and one
and a half somersaults and there's the
twist good synchronization Rebecca maybe
a little bit further away from the
diving board then licit so yep I'm
liking it let's see the judges think I
think eights on synchro should be in the
bag for them which is much more like it
the crowd obviously getting well behind
them I wanna talent and Lycia brag will
be in due course certainly early stage
of a diving development here and they'll
be happy enough with that just give them
a nice solid score of 72 now the USA
degree of difficulty again 3.0 inward
two-and-a-half somersaults for the
Americans currently just in second place
Wow they've rocking it today now I
didn't have them in my top three but I
might have to revisit my top three
because wow just one more time to go for
the US and if they carry on with this
this is the inward standing back was
spinning forward towards the diving
board fantastic synchronization the
judges have got to give them eights plus
for that execution a little bit off but
my goodness me if area near the 70 point
marked and that's going to keep them
well in contention the coaches like here
are definitely medal prospects after
that eighths on the right 7.5 on the
left and he reckons wholly on firmly a
tight grip on that second place hasn't
been Malaysia's day though certainly
hasn't then they come next Canada with
Emily Haman's and Jennifer Abel verse 2
and a half somersaults can they make
their way up into the top three
well I think they can they needed that
one Bob that was important they're a
little bit off the pace
Emily Hamer's of course her fourth
Olympic Games three medals in three
separate games looking for a fourth here
today and that certainly is going to
help their campaign there we are landing
on in the diving board swinging the arms
increasing the rotation little bit out
on the spin speeds they're entering the
water at the same time they're going to
get eighths across the board on that
I've seen better from the canadian pair
but when it needed to be it was right
there on the money so i think back up in
contention and of course as we've been
saying the judges don't see that replay
they have to judge in what they see
initially and you might have seen the
regular entry on the right nonetheless
points are pretty good at for canada
points have not really been forthcoming
from malaysia today reverse two and a
half the pang and zhang well that's
their best dive of today beautiful entry
in the water dive is close diver closest
to us they've certainly dug into the
bottom of their diving toybox and find
that one from somewhere because yeah
they haven't been on Form today at all
looked as though they were going to be a
little bit out of time there and I seem
to get it together in the end
and look at this beautiful entry into
the water so x1 execution mark will be
very high I think well let's go for
eight I think would be a fair one for
the synchro on that rainy day in London
taking a while for them to warm up isn't
it eight on the Left 7.5 and eights on
the right yeah a little bit happy with
that but all the damage done early on in
the diving program lastly but by no
means least late this meant to get and
feather over with their fourth round
dive well they looked as though they
were running away from a fire then as
they made their way down the diving
board two seem to be rushing into it a
little bit but then pushing the water
away they're in frustration but I think
it was actually okay they're certainly
not going to be a medal contention well
that's one of their better dives I think
they'll get them over 70 points there
you know synchronization is good they're
in alignment they're spinning at the
same time finishing a little bit low on
to the water but actually that's a good
tie from the Ukrainians
last round solar come their fourth round
score is this eight and eight point five
on the right and two eight on the left
so with six more dives to come eight
more dives to come in terms of the
competitors here we are with the fourth
round standings China USA Canada one two
three but look at the gap not much
between two and five really Australians
to have a chance to sneak back in there
great britain in seventh it looks like
Malaysia are tailed off going into the
final round so the final round of dives
in the women's synchronized 3-meter
springboard it would seem the gold is
going to China not unexpectedly but the
silver is very much still up for grabs
and here are a pair who are in
contention for that why do they can get
this right there in with two and a half
somersaults in the pike position last
dive for ten yet can yato and Francesca
dalla pay of Italy
all the pressure was on have they
responded with a big enough dive the
synchronization was good rotating at the
same speed and she's into the water at
the same time squeezing into that Pike
shape no daylight in between the thighs
and the chest that seems pretty good to
me
will it be enough though let's wait and
see what the judges think just waiting
for confirmation of the diving score
hasn't come up on the scoreboard as yet
we might have a little glitch in the
system
and be looking around waiting for it to
come here it is at last 70 1.10 probably
wanted a bit more than that to be a
medal contention 7.5 s and eights on the
right with an 8 point 5 4 re not quite
gonna be enough to sneak into bronze
today Australia represented by Smith &
Stratton for two and a half somersaults
one twist difficulty 3.0 as all these
are of course out there 3.1 this is back
to three for them in the pike position
Australia the pace but this could change
all that
oh it's a big die for them to finish on
it is normally their best dive but I'm
pretty sure there'd be a little bit
disappointed with their overall
performance today entering the water
they're good synchronization but both
over from vertical here we are one and a
half somersaults there's the one twist
great synchronization of both of them
over from vertical so actually the
judges the synchronized judges should
really go with that squeezing in a
valiant effort there but they are a
little bit off the pace what's happening
with the scoreboard but there's some
slight delays well the scores coming up
now sixty six point six zero there's a
lot of computations and calculations to
be done with the new scoring system I
think computer might be just struggling
a little bit well that puts Australia
into second place behind the Italians
and I think that means there will be no
Australian medal today and they're
getting enough as it is in the pool in
the swimming so I think we can there let
them off on this occasion well you won't
see perfection in action generally comes
from the Chinese and here comes the last
dive of Wu and hurt because she woke
going for three golds in a row in this
competition he comes their final dive
will it be their best dive yes it will
my goodness mate China leaving no room
for anyone to get anywhere near them
standing up there the teammates big
Chinese contingency here as you could
imagine looking to clean sweep as they
did last year and I'd say that's one
gold in the bag of a possible eight
already my goodness me booming shout
rewriting the history books more medals
for that particular athlete well big
smiles as well how many do you think
that's worth at home this is what the
judges will say is worth him going to
ten yet
we're up at nine point five s and 9s and
eight point five s execution they know
the job is well and truly done as they
take their total up to three hundred and
forty six point two zero and that is a
winning score
[Applause]
by some 32 points over Italy but there
are some other big names still to come
the USA and Canada after we've seen
Great Britain's final dive from Alesia
black and Rebecca gallantry yes Rebecca
on the left as you look at least here on
the right and they're going with back
two and a half somersaults
or they go Alyssia just making error on
a final type they're letting go of the
rotation a little bit earlier frustrate
there's a mum clapping away oh there's
nothing you could do there's no magic
rewind button
unfortunately the take-off is good
squeezing into the pike shape Rebekah's
dive is a reasonable one and this it
just letting go too early nothing you
could do once you've let go of your Pike
shape there she is
oops and just entering the water they're
sure to vertigo frustrating but a
valiant effort there for the girls today
of course being host nation they got a
place anywhere above eight would have
been a bonus for them and that's a shame
to finish on such a mediocre dive there
yeah
probably gonna mean that they'll be
battling it out with Malaysia for eighth
place not quite the finish they were
hoping for to send the crowd home happy
now the USA not going to overtake the
Chinese surely but to overtake the
Italians it's not going to take too much
gonna take 66 points for them to get
into second place that should be within
the compass of Johnson and Bryant on
their back
two and a half sour sauce
while they've done it I think that's
gonna be the us on the podium now I did
not predict that one I didn't see it
coming
they have been steadfast unwavering Wow
this could be the comeback for USA
diving they used to rule the roost when
it came to diving and I of course
Chinese are the supreme athletes in all
the disciplines us are working hard
behind the scenes Steve Foley of course
national performance director out there
for the past four years obviously
working his magic and let's see what the
total score is for the u.s. girls
because they're going to definitely be
in front of Italy now they know
seventy-two does put them in front of
Italy with a Ted Rogers three two one
all working well for them
as they take the silver medal at the
moment but it is not yet
cast in summer because we have jover
Abel Emily Haman's going for Canada but
they've got to get what 74 points very
nearly it's a lot to ask for this
forward two and a half some sorts one
twist yeah 74 is what they're looking at
you will take a point or two on the
Canadians final dive of this competition
well the pressure is on now have they
responded my goodness they're little bit
off their game today that's going to be
close I think you're maybe good enough
to take out the italians but is it good
enough to take out the u.s. here we go
landing on the end of the diving board
little bit of discrepancy on the timing
they're putting in the water at the same
time different distances for the board
I'm not sure what the judges are going
to make of it they have an exceptional
pairing maybe the judges will go with
them everyone in this orders were
holding their breath let's see what yes
they have just snuck into third place
and put the Italian sound of forth
they've done it by just over two points
2.6 to be absolutely accurate on it and
Canada sneaked into third the u.s. a
second I think they've just started to
realize what's happened there they had
to wait a little while for the scores to
come up but it is Canada who edged out
the Italians and the Australians will be
in fourth and fifth now it's a question
of who's going to finish bottom now
[Music]
Britain will be watching on see what
happens with Malaysia who are currently
in final place as the final dive of
Zhang and pango they've had a tough day
at the office not in the kind of form
that certainly got them the
qualification for this top eight only
straight Olympic final across the
qualification six months ago here in the
Aquatic Centre
I think panda leaner is suffering from
an injury so that's certainly hampered a
training lower back problem finishing
low on the water their synchronization
is pretty good though spin speeds have
on Andrews into the water a little over
from vertical as I mentioned so pretty
good tie for them let's see if it's good
enough to take them off the bottom spot
well they're fourth round I was by far
their best and that didn't really match
it sixty four point eight zero for Pam
and Chong and they will likely finish in
bottom place
last dive of the competition hasn't
really been fed her over and piss men
skiers day and they will complete their
day on the board at least with a forward
two and a half somersaults and one twist
really it's all about trying to move up
the standings as best they can
oh it ended up okay in the end
that I have a closest to it miss Mensa
girl and in way back from the end of the
diving board now let me tell you there
isn't very much spring there on the
springboard you need to be right on the
end to get the elevation you can just
see there a good foot back from the end
of the diving board she does so well to
execute the diver there's the twist into
the water that's really good sink remove
them up a notch but I think they left
themselves a little bit too much to do
nice overhead shot there just showing
how much the divers have to do to
complete now smile in a wave not a great
day for them sixth place for Miss
Minsker and Federer over with those
eights on the right hand side and 7.5
and 7 on the left all those scores with
the line through them do not count
towards their total score well maybe a
bonus medal here for the USA certainly a
silver look how excited they are
American team very very happy and they
finish some 25 points behind China and
then they do finish five points ahead of
Canada there's always a Canadian USA
rivalry and today it was the Americans
who just got the measure of the maple
leaf I think it probably means more to
the Americans it doesn't even else here
Emily Haman's their fourth Olympic medal
at a fourth Olympic Games that is
incredible the first woman in the
history to ever do that in the sport of
diving
what it either now of course China won
all but won that gold medal in Beijing
Matthew Mitchum stopping that run four
years ago well they're off and running
again at Wu and her with the winning
score and Wu's third gold medal in the
3-meter springboard with different
partners second USA there Canada Italy
in Australia missing out great britain
fishing in seven
[Applause]
well look at that the Americans are
absolutely delighted they'll have their
medal sir me very soon but when we came
into this I didn't ask you Leon who you
thought might be in the mix and yeah we
kind of downplayed the chance of the
Americans but I think there's something
about this Paul it's worked so well for
the swimmers now saina work really well
for their divers as well yeah certainly
they're obviously
thriving on the momentum that's been
created in the pool look at Jennifer
able their tears or why and this is so
tough for the divers you know it's a
straight final the Olympic Games is a
bit of a game of life you know if you
make one slight mistake in a pairing it
can be all over as we saw there wasn't
working out today for the Italians or
the Australians in fourth and fifth
respectively and I thought they would
have been mixing it up a little bit more
smiles around Emily Haman's what an
athlete for Olympic Games in for medals
Wow truly extraordinary and look at the
amount of people here local time is 346
on a Sunday afternoon and that is
absolutely round we're looking at 16 17
thousand people here watching diving and
quite right to diving is one of the hot
tickets in town and of course Tom Daley
day tomorrow which will mean that this
place will be rammed it's good to see
diving shining in the spotlight and that
was an exciting contest certainly wasn't
you know a downto that was certainly
down to the last dive to see where those
medal what medals were going to go apart
from the gold which right from the start
I just had a sneaky suspicion the women
Sharon heezy or her Z we're going to
romp home once again as Olympic
champions and that they have done of
course it will be the Tim metre synchro
an Avenger you know very much about Leon
having won silver in Athens in 2004 we
also have of course the men's equivalent
3-meter springboard competition and then
we have the women's 10 metre synchro as
well before we get involved in the
individual should explain of course this
goes straight to final it's top eight
here once we get into the individual
events later in the week and indeed into
next week there will be preliminaries
then there'll be so many files in the
nuddy finals
awaiting the medal ceremony he might
take a while for the Americans to calm
down before the guests she kid in there
and that meant so much them in there it
may be their expectancy coming in here
was they weren't gonna do anything well
I think you can't come in with with that
kind of focus I know those girls have
you know I think every athlete you know
out there today dreams of standing on
that podium and when it comes down to it
it's about making each and every one of
those five dives count and it's about
being consistent you're going to hear me
use that word a lot over these two and a
half weeks because it is about
consistency you cannot afford to do for
exceptional dives and then one mediocre
dive each and every dive has to be
consistently exceptional to stand on
that podium and that's what we saw from
from Team USA today the girls over you
know in their early 20s and a very very
impressive partnership and they you know
held it together when it counted and you
saw the Canadians wobbling they ended up
with the bronze in the end but mistakes
and a little bit of uncertainty from the
Italians in the Australians who I
thought would be out there mixing it up
a little bit closer for those top spots
I just wonder if some of these pairings
we won't see again you talk about the
Canadians is it likely or unlikely we'll
see Haman's and Abel in four years time
I would say unlikely but I don't want to
speak firmly I mean she's 30 years old
now and I continue diving till I was 30
and I'll tell you it hurts a lot more
when you get into your late 20s Emily of
course was an exceptional platform diver
Olympic medalist and world champion in
fact on the platform and then did the
sensible thing and retired to the
springboard it's a little bit closer to
the water it doesn't tend to beat you up
quite as much and my goodness me she is
such an all-round diver competing in the
springboard synchros on both events of
platform Wow she'll go down in history
the first woman ever to win four Olympic
medals at four consecutive games
what about pointers for the three meter
individual are we again looking at China
ruling the roost in that yeah I think
you would be foolish to bet against
China you know they are certainly head
and shoulders certainly in the women's
springboard event both in the sinker and
the individual their head and shoulders
above the rest of the field but of
course you and I have sat through
many competitions but we can see some
interesting things happen I think it was
in the men's three metre synchro
springboard in Athens you know two days
after Peter and I stood on the podium we
saw a calamity to say the least where
the Chinese of course ended up failing
their last dive in coming last which you
know I don't think anyone saw coming so
I don't want to sit here now and give
the audience the impression that it's
all sewn up the Chinese you know it's
they are they are the frontrunners the
bookies favourites if you will but you
know they still go to perform in this
order - you know in this arena with all
the eyes of the world on them and it's
no mean feat I think it's unlikely we
will ever see a 3-meter springboard
event synchro event like that ever again
because there's just so many memories of
the Greeks who who again got host nation
spot probably would have been there
otherwise who went on to win it and also
the fact that somebody jumped in the
diving pit in the middle of the
competition something else I've never
ever seen again or before you know
that's right and as we say anything can
happen so I'm not wishing for anything
like that to happen once again but who
knows what the yes stay stay tuned
everyone stay tuned you never know
what's going to happen in the in the
diving pool we have all week and next
week just a remarkable reaction from
both the Americans and the Canadians and
of course they at the moment just doing
their poolside interviews wave from the
British competitors and you see a black
and Rebecca Gannon treat USA would not
otherwise have been here had it not been
host nation but they got a great
exhibition not actually finishing and
bottom rung we'll give them a super
coach yeah well we talked about Alisha
as a prospect for the future that
there's so many good young divers that
rot all around the world they're coming
through at this stage and this is a good
platform literally for them to move on
from great springboard for them to
bounce off more diving metaphors at yeah
I mean it's fantastic so listen a
youngest competitor 15 years old gets to
compete in front of a home crowd in a
home country wow what an experience I
can't wait to speak to the girls
afterwards to see how they find it yes
of course they're going to look back on
on their performances say dive number
three and dive know
five were under pal we could have done
better but you know to be here to move
themselves off the eighth place which
they were seeded in he's an achievement
in its own right and you know they look
great out there and as you mentioned Bob
Alessia as a bright future ahead of her
I think noticed the camera kept cutting
away to work to her mom who and I know
her mom well and she was certainly
beside ourselves with nerves I'm glad
her daughter didn't share the same kind
of nervous energy that her mum seemed to
be you know having to deal with their as
the camera cut away to a new scoring
system today or a kind of advancement of
the scoring system today how does it
work well it's a modified slightly in
order to try and make it fair and I when
I was explaining at the beginning it is
quite difficult to explain
you know succinctly because it is
relatively complex however the intention
behind it is actually very very
important and that is to try and make it
fairer you're trying to eliminate you
know it's a subjective sport but you're
trying to eliminate any bias that might
be there so you're always taking the
highest and lowest score if you're
always trying to average everything out
but of course this is a synchronized
diving competition so you need to wait
the you know the scores towards the
synchro to make that the most important
element otherwise people will start
concentrating more on the execution if
the if there's more points if you will
to be gained from that so I think you
know FINA have done the right thing you
know you've got more judges on Paul's
side now than I've ever seen before but
I think the intention behind it is the
right one and I'm hoping it worked and
certainly the results we're looking at
today were the results I know sometimes
we sit here barb and I say oh hang on a
second in my opinion or near maybe we
can look at this and say that was an
unfair finishing order but today you
know that the judging system and the
judges got it right this is the fourth
Olympics we've had synchronized diving I
think a few people initially thought
it's gonna work it's really gonna take
off it's now very much part and parcel
of the diving program yeah I think it's
I think it's the highlight in many ways
of the diving program because you do not
need to be a diving expert to know
what's going on in fact I could probably
take any one of these audience members
and put them on the pool side there as a
judge and they wouldn't actually be too
far away judging the synchro now they
wouldn't know anything about the
execution they wouldn't know they're two
and a half from there three and a half
might even know they might not know
they're tucked from their Pike but
certainly former sink is spectator
friendly I'm sure the audience will
agree at home that after a while you
know listening to Bob and I of course
you can get into it and know which is a
good splash and a bad splash but more
importantly you can see the
synchronization and the marine plays are
fantastic and it really brings the sport
alive and it's yeah as I said spectator
friendly and I think that's its greatest
selling point and something else we'll
see next week Leon when we get to the
individual it's just how many countries
now there was a time when you look at a
selection of countries and there wasn't
much beyond that but diving seems to
have really expanded in terms of
countries who are doing it now yeah
that's right I mean we saw that for sure
the World Cup the test event here in
February the Olympic Games the IOC are
very much on the ball and they say okay
you can have your synchro in diving but
it needs to be a straight final and you
can have your individual event but it
needs to be capped so you're only going
to see 32 competitors in each of the
individual events so you won't see the
super spread that we saw at the test
event where everyone was fiercely trying
to earn those qualification spots but
yeah diving is one of those events many
many countries around the world take
part and and certainly it's thriving the
world over and quite right too I maybe
I'm slightly biased but quite like -
it's a question you get asked a lot I
get asked quite a bit as well is why are
China so dominant is it because it's
pretty much a job for the Chinese divers
rather than a sport yeah well you know
I'm sure you've heard you know many a
pundit kind of share their their views
on Chinese dominance in many many
different sports I mean they're you know
fighting with the US for for that number
one spot on the on the overall medal
table now there's a couple of reasons
why they're exceptional diving they have
well it's a game with numbers we've
heard that before
but they have a system in China which
works very well now that system isn't
particularly fair or some people might
say ethical where you know you give your
child away pretty much to these sporting
institutions and they are given the
opportunity to train all hours every
single day for year upon year upon year
and the ones who do not break in that
system are the ones that we see here
today standing on top of the podium so
it's a very very different
system - what we have here I started
diving as a as a hobby a hyperactive
child who was you know channelled into
sport to try and give my parents arrest
and I find it I found a sport that I
enjoyed but I wasn't really I wasn't
given away at three years old so it's
the moment that well it seems the USA
have definitely been waiting for and
Canada - it is the victory ceremony for
the women's synchronized three meter
spring or just to clear up the teams
below third finishing an eighth were
Malaysia Great Britain in seventh
Federer over and Paz Mexico of Ukraine
in sixth Australia in fifth the Italians
just missing out by just about two
points from getting third place but here
come those who did make the top three
and comes the presentation party and the
appropriate flags which I think we'll
get right at the diving
proudly walking in there Zeke booming
ship taking their position getting ready
to go through something it's pretty
routine for them these days picking up a
gold medal not quite so routine for the
pair's either side of them however for
Abel and Emily Haman's to the right and
to the left the American pair who
haven't stopped smiley and I think since
they actually got out of the diving bit
earlier arm abigail Johnston and Kelsey
Bryant
yes mr. happy Mackay IOC member for Oman
who will be involved in the presentation
and representing the governing body for
all water sports swimming diving water
polo and sink rope
yes parlo Borelli the Honorary Secretary
of FINA no smart the outfits turns the
presentation party with the the medals
and the flowers
and the bronze medal going to Jennifer
Abel and back again for war Emily
Haman's getting used to this routine
she's been doing it for many years and
it still means just as much to hurt to
have that bronze medal placed around her
neck another one to add to the
collection
Jennifer Abel as well as another one
which she can cherish as well
they're good memories of London 2012 for
those two and even better memories for
the American pet were about to receive
there's a great tonight at the end the
Canadians had absolutely the last time a
bit better and they will be looking at
silver but bronze will do there on the
platform on the metal platform once
again for Canada
[Music]
so a medal for the USA goes to Abigail
Johnston and Kelsey Bryant and you can
tell by the look on their faces it means
a great deal to them and probably
unexpectedly two predictions before this
event Americans weren't close to a
silver medal but they were consistent
all the way through good opening dives
and then they had an exceptional third
round dive which lifted them pretty much
clear of the pack for second place and
America add to their tally in the poor
swimming medals last night a diving
medal today for Abigail Johnston and
Kelsey Bryant but no real surprise I
suppose everybody would have predicted
it and pretty much everybody would have
got it right that's China just so
dominant in women's events you might get
usurped in one of the men's events
possibly later in the week but not today
in the women's and a looming ship will
step onto the platform now she has done
on two previous occasions to collect the
gold medal this time with her Zi and a
Chinese loving that's rather unusual way
of picking your medals we go for a
little walk because they don't circuit
of the medal podium
great Chinese response from the Oh a lot
of Chinese flags out there well Chinese
fans who follow these divers all over
the world they go everywhere they go and
not too far behind and a good raw for
the Chinese yes
it's again nosy and we'll Ming chef pick
up the gold medal in the opening diving
event of London 2012 the women's
synchronized 3-meter springboard final
probably the first of very many over the
next couple of weeks for China
of the People's Republic of China
[Music]
[Applause]
madam Jamis you
so there'll be a lot of very happy
Chinese spectators here in London who
will be going away happy but I don't me
the smiles will be quite as broad as
they are on the face of Bryant and
Johnson the two Americans who will I
feel still be smiling at about five
pounds it's time that's so delighted
quite like - it's their moment - to soak
it all up look how impressive those
medals are I'm loving the the branding
and the particularly the size of the
medal mine isn't that big I can I can
tell you my medal that is but well that
was an exciting start to the exciting
start to the diving I just wonder what
else is in store
Emily Hamer's of course four Olympic
medals for Olympic Games Rumi Shou there
she is
three Olympic gold medals in this
particular event look at the Chinese
support we can see there was no problem
today with any of the seats being empty
this place was full to capacity great
and long may it continue well they've
got this routine down to a fine art now
they the the waving they have the little
Chinese flags in their hands obviously
just picking out all the Chinese
continuing there's plenty buying that's
plenty you are the side of the pool
where they up and they will do a full
circuit the Canadians at the back
enjoying their moments were very
supportive team the Canadian team a very
close-knit team as well and they all be
trying to get their vantage point to get
some pictures but their divers because
may not be too many chances for the
Canadians to get on the medal rostrum
next couple of weeks they vote to Alex
Day party and we're very glad to see
he's back after his recent troubles yeah
diving obviously no tourists dangerous
Alexander Day party you know three-time
Olympic medalist already its head on the
diving board when he was training in
Rome and very dear friend of mine safe
to say he's fully recovered from that
stitched up and once again ready for
action you'll see here me featuring in
the men's three me to synchronize where
he'll be looking to win another Olympic
medal to add to his collection of two
silvers already both in the individual
three meter diving board and
a couple of days time the Tron in the
week we have the 10 metre synchro
tomorrow
and what how many photographs have been
taken to these two around the world lets
me know China China and diving go hand
in hand with popularity I mean it's
probably the third most popular sport in
there in the land and of course these
athletes superstars back home know for
sure Tom Daley has you know an
extraordinary number of followers on on
Chinese Twitter so that brings to an end
the women's synchronized three meter
spring or just to remind you again of
the result wheeling ship and Ezzy
China's first gold in the dining event
probably not their last either
Abigail Johnson and Kelsey Bryant of the
USA in second Canada represented by
Emily Haman's and Jennifer Abel with the
bronze medal and just missing out
Italy's tenia Kenyatta
francesca dalla Pape and the Australians
maybe a bit disappointing today
Annabelle Smith and Charlene Stratton
who have hoped to be in the mix just
weren't today so I'm half of Leon Taylor
and myself Bob Bala
thank you for joining us hope you'll
join us at the same time tomorrow for
what we hope will be a very exciting 10
metre platform synchro final join us
them from us here in London at the
Aquatic Centre it's goodbye
[Music]